<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI>
    <!-- begin TEI header -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <!-- title statement -->
            <titleStmt>
                <title>David P. Boder Interviews Anna Kaletska; September 26, 1946; Wiesbaden, Germany</title>
                <author>David P. Boder</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Text encoding</resp>
                    <name>Shiva Srivastava</name>
                </respStmt>
                <!--
                    <respStmt>
                    <resp>Transcription</resp>
                    <name>[name]</name>
                    </respStmt>
                -->
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>English Translation</resp>
                    <name>David P. Boder</name>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Editor</resp>
                    <name>Eben E. English</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <!-- publication statement -->
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Paul V. Galvin Library</publisher>
                <pubPlace>
                    <address>
                        <addrLine>Illinois Institute of Technology</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Chicago, IL</addrLine>
                    </address>
                </pubPlace>
                <date>2009</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>Copyright (c) 2009 Paul V. Galvin Library, Illinois Institute of Technology</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <!-- source description -->
            <sourceDesc>
                <recordingStmt>
                    <recording type="audio" dur="PT58M21.244S" id="kaletskaA_9-164B_9-165_9-166">
                        <broadcast>
                            <bibl>
                                <lang value="primary" norm="yi">Yiddish</lang>
                                <note type="spools" n="1">9-164B</note>
                                <note type="spools" n="2">9-165</note>
                                <note type="spools" n="3">9-166</note>
                                <placeName ref="Wiesbaden"/>
                            </bibl>
                        </broadcast>
                        <date>1946-09-26</date>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>Recorded by</resp>
                            <name>David P. Boder</name>
                        </respStmt>
                        <equipment>
                            <p>Armour wire recorder</p>
                        </equipment>
                    </recording>
                </recordingStmt>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <!-- profile desription -->
        <profileDesc>
            <!--
                <textDesc id="" n="transcription">
                <channel mode="s">interview</channel>
                <constitution type="single">transcript of a continuously recorded interaction among the specified participants</constitution>
                <derivation type="transcription">transcribed in the languages used by the participants</derivation>
                <domain type="documentary"/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction type="complete"/>
                <preparedness type="none"/>
                <purpose type="documentary"/>
                </textDesc>
            -->
            <textDesc id="kaletskaA_en" n="english_translation">
                <channel mode="s">interview</channel>
                <constitution type="single">English translation of a transcript of a continuously recorded interaction among the specified participants</constitution>
                <derivation type="translation">English translation of the interview transcript</derivation>
                <domain type="documentary"/>
                <factuality type="fact"/>
                <interaction type="complete"/>
                <preparedness type="none"/>
                <purpose type="documentary"/>
            </textDesc>
            <particDesc>
                <listPerson>
                    <person id="boderD" role="interviewer">
                        <persName>
                            <addName type="honorific" full="abb">Dr.</addName>
                            <forename>David</forename>
                            <forename type="middle">Pablo</forename>
                            <surname>Boder</surname>
                        </persName>
                    </person>
                    <person id="kaletskaA" role="interviewee">
                        <persName>
                            <forename>Anna</forename>
                            <surname>Kaletska</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <persName type="alias">
                            <forename>Anna</forename>
                            <surname>Kovitzka</surname>
                        </persName>
                        <sex value="2">female</sex>
                        <age>34</age>
                        <birth when="1912-09-25" ref="Poland"/>
                        <faith>Jewish</faith>
                        <nationality key="Poland"/>
                        <state type="marital_status">
                            <desc>married</desc>
                        </state>
                        <trait type="role_during_holocaust">
                            <desc>victim</desc>
                        </trait>
                        <trait type="tattoo">
                            <desc>82529Δ</desc>
                        </trait>
                        <event type="invasion" ref="Kielce">
                            <ab/>
                        </event>
                        <event type="internment" ref="Grodno Ghetto">
                            <ab/>
                        </event>
                        <event type="internment" ref="Auschwitz concentration camp">
                            <ab/>
                        </event>
                        <event type="internment" ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp">
                            <ab/>
                        </event>
                        <event type="liberation" ref="Kaunitz" when="1945-04-01" resp="us">
                            <ab/>
                        </event>
                    </person>
                </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
        </profileDesc>
        <!-- encoding description -->
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <p>Marked items include: speaker turns, times of speaker turns, languages, geographic entities, camps/ghettos, and glossary terms.</p>
                <p>The English translation was edited using the guidelines of the Chicago Manual of Style, 15th edition.</p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- end TEI header -->
    <text>
        <body>
            <!-- include the locations file -->
            <include href="voth_locations_tei.xml" parse="xml" xpointer="vothL"/>
            <!-- include the camps file -->
            <include href="voth_camps_tei.xml" parse="xml" xpointer="vothC"/>
            <!-- include the glossary file -->
            <include href="voth_glossary_tei.xml" parse="xml" xpointer="vothG"/>
            <!-- begin transcription -->
            <!-- <div> -->
            <!-- paste transcription here -->
            <!-- </div> -->
            <!-- end transcription -->
            <!-- begin English translation -->
            <div corresp="#kaletskaA_en">
                <!-- begin spool 9-164B -->
                <div lang="en">
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1.757" end="x">This is reproduction spool 9-164B. The beginning of the interview of Anna Kalestka who in the book appears as Anna Kovitska. November 14 1950, <placeName ref="Chicago">Chicago</placeName>. Boder.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="31.765" end="x"><placeName ref="Wiesbaden">Wiesbaden</placeName>, September . . . <placeName ref="Wiesbaden">Wiesbaden</placeName>, September 26, 1946. Already at three o'clock. I have to leave this town at five to get to Frankfurt and then to <placeName ref="Paris">Paris</placeName>. [unintelligible] a bit personal. It is the last day of my work in Germany . . . which to a large extent, I have officially to be thankful to the UNNRA, and unofficially to our friend, Jack Thompson, of the Chicago Tribune, who has done so much to realize, to help me to realize this project.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="69.899" end="x">I have before me a young woman . . . a young woman by the name of Chana or Anna Kaletska, meaning that her husband's name was Kaletski, and she is going to talk to us . . . Are you going to talk in Yiddish? [She apparently nods affirmatively.] She is going to talk to us in Yiddish.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="89.571" end="x">[In Yiddish] Now then, Mrs. Kaletski, will you please tell us where you are from and where you were when all the troubles and, so to speak, worries of the war started?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="104.417" end="x">I am from Poland somewhere between . . . and . . . [This part is not clear.]</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="122.337" end="x">And where were you when the Germans came to Poland?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="127.165" end="x">In 1939, September 1st, I was still with my parents together in <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>. My father was an important citizen in <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName> for about thirty-five years. Together with us on the night of Friday- from Thursday to Friday it was- there happened to be with us my brother from Potianice and a child of my oldest sister, a grandchild twelve years old. At six o'clock in the morning the first bombs fell over <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>. I went down with my parents into the cellar, but my father did not want to go. He said: "From this one cannot hide in the cellar." Then he "said" a chapter from the Psalms. My youngest brother was in the war on the Polish side. And with it I thought that the world had come to an end. To lose my youngest brother! I did not want to live any more. So naive I was then, to think that all I would lose in the war was my youngest brother. Once during the first days of September I got up especially early—five o'clock in the morning. There wasn't a single German to be seen on the street. So I said: "Mother, dear, maybe it was only a dream. Maybe they are really not here." Unfortunately, it was not a dream.. They were there, and they were there for a long time. My father had to leave his home to hide somewhere in the suburb. The <term ref="#vothG_gestapo">Gestapo</term> was looking for him. I remained alone with my mother in five rooms, and all through the night I was clinging to the window, running around in search. Where are the people who used to come every night- every evening- to see my father? Where are the grandchildren, who are afraid to cross the street and to come upstairs? Nobody was there.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="263.303" end="x">Please tell the facts.</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="269.653" end="x">In November I departed with my parents from . . . (name of locality incomprehensible). We were told there was a prisoners' camp—Pshemish. I went across to the Russian side. I was not far from <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>, and there I found everybody alive, and I looked for a place where I could bring over my parents. But in March it was already too late to bring somebody over, and so I remained in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. Among the Russians the Jews lived just like all the other peoples.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="299.711" end="x">How did you get from <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName> to <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="302.242" end="x">I just got over there.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="310.314" end="x">You alone?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="311.704" end="x">All alone without my folks, without a means to communicate with them. I remained in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="320.943" end="x">How old are you now?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="322.990" end="x">Thirty-four years. Yesterday was my birthday.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="326.724" end="x">On the eve of the New Year?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="328.786" end="x">In <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName> the Jews lived just like the other people. First there were those who lived in Poland before, and then there were those who came from the zone occupied by the Germans. And they all lived together. Some lived in the synagogues or in the streets, but still they all lived together. Somehow I adjusted myself in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. One has to live. The only thing was the terrible worry about my parents, and the homesickness. And all day and all night fire was pouring over <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>, and within a single twenty-four hours sixty per-cent of the city was destroyed; and we remained alive. I lived on a street in No. 9; No. 11 burned down. No's. 27,23, and 9- I remained alive. At No. 11 and at one side of No. 9, there fell a bomb, destroying everything. I remained alive- and again there came the Germans. In a monstrous fashion they chased people through the streets, and it soon started all over. This was in the East, with special laws. In a few days I got the idea that my husband was alive.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="425.896" end="x">It occurred to you, or you knew?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="427.442" end="x">I got the idea that my husband was alive and somewhere hiding in a village among the Germans, a prisoner. I wanted to run, but where to run? They didn't threaten me. I had to wait, and in a few days he came.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="446.589" end="x">He returned?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="447.777" end="x">Yes.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="449.198" end="x">What does it mean- you got an idea'? Somebody has written to you?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="451.714" end="x">No. At that time there came people who were together with him- with my man. And so they first brought me an idea.. [She apparently has used the Hebrew word "yidie" which means "message".] And my man succeeded in "blacking himself across." *The word "black" is a designation for illegal action, as in "black market" or "black papers," and it has become a verb- to do something illegal is often spoken of as "to black." *, to <placeName ref="Vawkavysk">Wolkowysk</placeName> and to mingle in with other prisoners. He had an uncle there, and so we got together. During the summer they still let us live in our apartment, although my husband had to work very hard, from six o'clock in the morning until six o'clock at night, together with all the others. And we still had at home some belongings, and we sold them, and we ate, and we hoped that possibly we might survive. The first of November we were driven into the <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">Ghetto</term>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="502.699" end="x">Where?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="503.574" end="x">In <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>, into the <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term>. They arranged two <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term>, one in Slobodka [The name Slobodka often is used to designate the poorer suburbs, or slums.] and one <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term> in the yard of the synagogue. At the beginning, the day when we came to the <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term> the wires were not ready, and it did not make such a terrible impression. But the next day everything was fenced up and there was an inscription on the gate- "From here one does not return." . . . [She is very much upset and for the next two sentences the wire is not clear.] We have learned that the Jew should never give up hope, and his spirit should never falter. But the heart was heavy. It was hard to bear. I was in my ninth month. We used to live like affluent citizens, my father-in-law, my man, and my sister-in-law. Now we were given a room of eight and one-half cubic meters,-- no, squares; I don't know how many cubic meters there were. And there I was to give birth to my child. One day they opened the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName>, and every Jew was permitted to go into his home to fetch some things. Then my father-in-law went back to his home, and he saw the destruction of the home for which he has been working for thirty-years- and he returned gravely ill. He never got well again.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="583.424" end="x">What do you mean- he saw the destruction?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="585.424" end="x">There was his home, and he saw how it was ransacked and ruined.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="588.768" end="x">Who ransacked and ruined it?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="590.658" end="x">We left the house just as it was, with only the things on our body and a few bundles in our hands. And everything else had to be left. And the people, of course, who lived around- what did they care about the Jews! They just waited for such a moment. They went inside. The things of value the <term ref="#vothG_gestapo">Gestapo</term> themselves hauled away. My father-in-law had been working hard all his life, and when he saw what had become of his home, he took badly sick, and he remained sick up until the end. The 26th of November I gave birth to my child in the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName> in my room, because there was not yet a Jewish hospital. The doctor- and everybody—tried to comfort me. On the third day after my child was born, we were informed that we would be driven into barracks to <placeName ref="Kiełbasin concentration camp" type="camp">Kelbasin</placeName>, six kilometers away from <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. There were seventy thousand Russian prisoners, and after six weeks there remained only six thousand. To such a place they wanted to drive us away.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="679.203" end="x">What do you mean, there remained only six thousand?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="681.812" end="x">They died off from spotted fever, from various contagious diseases, as well as from starvation. I was not in <placeName ref="Kiełbasin concentration camp" type="camp">Kelbasin</placeName>, but a part of the <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName> Jews a year later were in <placeName ref="Kiełbasin concentration camp" type="camp">Kelbasin</placeName>, and there they died by the thousands. In the middle of <placeName ref="Kiełbasin concentration camp" type="camp">Kelbasin</placeName> there was an open pit, where they would throw the children, and they did not cover it up until it was full. Dead Jewish children. We did not go then to <placeName ref="Kiełbasin concentration camp" type="camp">Kelbasin</placeName>. They let us stay in the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName> for a year.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="715.763" end="x">[In English] This concludes spool . . . This concludes Spool 164 which the . . . for 27 minutes was taken by Mr. Jack Matzner and then taken over by Mrs. Anna Kaletska. We are going over with Mrs. Kaletska to Spool 165. We are going over with Mrs. Kaletska to spool . . . <placeName ref="Wiesbaden">Wiesbaden</placeName>, September the 26th, 1946. My last day of interviewing in Germany—I usually do not mention my name in these spools, but I am finishing a piece of work which I hope will do some good.</u>
                    <!-- end spool 9-164B -->
                    <!-- begin spool 9-165 -->
                    <u who="#boderD" start="750.882" end="x">[In English] <placeName ref="Wiesbaden">Wiesbaden</placeName>, September the 26th, 1946. Last day of the project in Germany. I have before me Mrs. Anna Kaletska, 34 years old, who will continue her report from Spool 164 to Spool 165. She's rather emotional and she cannot mobilize [unintelligible] with her voice [unintelligible]. Volume control is a bit high, which may not give a very good reproduction but it will be enough for transcription.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="780.397" end="x">[In Yiddish] And so you had your baby? What was it, a boy or a girl?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="785.381" end="x">A little girl.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="786.162" end="x">And you continued living for a whole year in the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName>?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="789.583" end="x">In the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="789.942" end="x">Now go ahead.</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="790.848" end="x">At the end of the summer people began to arrive from everywhere. From here, from there, from <placeName ref="Brest">Brest-Litovak</placeName>, from <placeName ref="Lviv">Lemberg</placeName>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="802.764" end="x">Did you know anybody in <placeName ref="Slonim">Slonim</placeName>? Do you remember any name?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="806.701" end="x">There was a Jew from <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName> in <placeName ref="Slonim">Slonim</placeName>, a son of a very prominent, wealthy man from <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>, Chaim Zagalski, with his daughter; he ran away from <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>, and they were heard of from <placeName ref="Slonim">Slonim</placeName>. And we sent a man from <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName> to bring him over. So he found the door nailed shut, the house empty; Chaim Zagalski was not there any more. There were left in <placeName ref="Slonim">Slonim</placeName> about two hundred Jews, out of a population of nine thousand Jews before the start of the slaughter, or possibly even more- I don't know. There were a lot of refugees from districts previously doomed by the Germans. I did not know the district of <placeName ref="Slonim">Slonim</placeName>. There was a great <placeName ref="Slonim">Slonim</placeName> rabbi, whose name I don't know. And these two hundred Jews had numbers hung on them (the Christians made them wear them), and they had to report every day to the square, an place of roll call, and they were sent to work. Work! We too had worries about work! The day my man was working, we had hope to survive that day. But when people came to the gates of the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName> and said, "no more work required," that was a dark day. We knew it was coming. November 1, 1942, the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName> was surrounded. Every few steps stood an armed German, with his gun ready, and at some distance on the hill machine guns. They told us nothing, but they took us "to work." We knew what that meant. And nearby were Russians, Poles; not all but many were waiting for what they could inherit from the Jews. Possibly they had waited so that in case the Germans themselves would not put an end to us, they could step in.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="914.809" end="x">Step in for what?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="915.747" end="x">So they could consummate the terrible deed. That is what we were told from <placeName ref="Brest">Brest-Litovsk</placeName> and other Ukranian cities. And in Russia, as far as <placeName ref="Volgograd">Stalingrad</placeName> and the Ural [mountains], the Germans did it themselves. They could not relinquish the "sacred labor", and they had their mission. However, it did not start that day, nor later. With a sadistic forethought, they told us: "Have no care, this will become a labor <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term>, my word of honor." said Herr Ehrlich, the <term ref="#vothG_gestapo">Gestapo</term> chief, to the Community Council. "Mass murder! Oh, no; that is out of the question- deportation, neither!! It will be converted into a work-<term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term>, no more loafing. And believe me, my word of honor." Believe his word of honor! In two weeks it started. First we saw them transporting the inhabitants of the smaller towns, from Slobodka,—on horse carts, old, broken down, sick people, and on foot the young ones; towards Bialystok they were led. And when they were through with the small towns, it commenced in Grodne. First came Slobodka. The first street. . . . my father,—that is, my father-in-law,—I must save my child. Possibly we should get away at night to some Poles, old acquaintances, and hide there. My husband, myself, my sister-in-law, and a girl friend who was with us, we shall get away to the <term ref="#vothG_partisans">partisans</term>, and Father with the child should remain with the Poles. But he refused. And so it was. He resigned himself to death. To me he said: "Take the child and save yourselves. Go to the other <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term>. There they are still allowed to remain." I was the first to go over to the second <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term> with the child. In a few days came my man. Father told him: "For the sake of the child, go!" He himself remained there. His younger daughter Zina- he could not abandon her, and they both went off with a transport, most probably to <placeName ref="Treblinka concentration camp" type="camp">Treblinka</placeName>. Within a week they started the <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term> in the yard of the synagogue. The most horrible was that the Jewish Police (at the beginning we were not told about the horrible role they would have to play) they came and led us, assembled for the slaughter there, to the synagogue, at night. Every few nights we would sit up—I, my man (the child was asleep, all dressed, and we expected the police to come after us. Every night we said Vida (the prayer of those who expect to die) of our own composition, and forgave each other, but they did not come. My man worked then as a carpenter (he is a lumber sorter by trade), and this kept us there. Once my man said: "I can't make peace with them. Our child must be saved even if we two shall die. We have nobody any more. You look like a Christian; get out with the child. Put it next to a Christian orphanage. Orphans also may be lucky sometimes. I can't want her to die." It snowed that night. It was 25 degrees cold. [Below zero centigrade.] Sixteen Jews fell at the gate in the first attempt to escape. I went over the wires in the second attempt, and my man handed me the child, and I carried her away.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1152.222" end="x">How did you get over the wires?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1153.753" end="x">My man set up a chair for me. He raised one wire, and I crawled through.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1158.924" end="x">Weren't those electric wires?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1161.564" end="x">No, then they had no electric wires. He handed me the child. And I went out in the street. I removed the yellow patch, and I went down the street. It was eight o'clock. At nine o'clock it was curfew hour. I did not know where to go. All at once I remembered a Christian woman whom I happened to know, and I went to her and said: "This is all that I have got; take the child and carry it to an orphanage. Say, you have found it in the street. I am returning to my man, and we shall perish together." She started to wring her hands, a Christian woman whom I had possibly seen only twice before. And she said: "I am afraid (the Poles were threatened with death for such things); put her in the street. I will come out of the house with a neighbor woman; we shall come out as if by accident. I will pick up the child and take her tomorrow to the orphanage, but you go away immediately." And so she has taken my child. I went with her down to the door, and there I stood across the street, hidden in the gate, and I saw how my child was lying on the snow. And here, I could not pick her up, the child that I had brought into the world! I knew that that will save her life. That is what I hoped. [A few words in this sentence are not clear. She is sobbing, and even by slowing down the wire and listening to this section over and over, I have been able to understand only about three words. I do not think that the translation of the phrase "the child I brought into the world" is entirely correct.] In a few minutes she came out of the house and picked up the child. I ran away through the streets of <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>, and I didn't think of the curfew—that I might be caught,—and I didn't know how to get back to the <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term>, as it was such a late hour. There was a Christian woman in the city, with whom I had once worked during the time of the Soviets. I stepped in to her, and a girl friend of mine was hiding there. I entered the house, and I said, "Panuvka *This is a respectful and at the same time endearing name for a Polish woman. *, I don't have my child any more. How light my hands feel!" Then she said, "Twenty-six hours you have suffered to bring her into the world, and now you will suffer as long as you live." I didn't ask her for much—just to keep me over night. She couldn't help me for much longer, because on Sunday no one could show himself in the city. The Germans were grabbing the people and dragging them to work in Germany. I wanted to return to the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName>. Then thousand Jews were deported that day. The <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName> was surrounded. One couldn't get in, nor could one get out. Part were going to <placeName ref="Treblinka concentration camp" type="camp">Treblinka</placeName>, and to get in one also didn't know how. I ran into a Christian—he was a working man. [Recording not clear.] I told him I am a Jewess—"I can't get into the <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term>." And he said, "Get out of the city. You do not look Jewish. Go where ever you can, but don't remain here. You see here it burns." And so I departed alone, without papers, into the woods. I did not know the roads. Through the woods, into a Russian village. I entered. "Give me some water." If one is alive, one has to drink water. And sometimes one has to eat. Everybody gave me something. I did not look Jewish, but they knew—what else could be driving me in the snow through the woods? Everyone kept me for one night.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1376.760" end="x">The Christians?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1377.401" end="x">The Christians—I can't complain. Everybody gave me warm water to wash myself. They gave me food, so that I should have strength to wander farther. And there was a preacher—A Christian, a Catholic. He hid me "for strength" for eight days. But it drove me back to <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">Grodno</placeName> to find out what was going on. The priest encountered some Jews that were going to work. She he asked them: "Do you know whether Jack Kovitzki is there?" So they said: "He is there, he has remained alive." Three thousand Jews were still in <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">Grodno</placeName>. So he said, "Tell him that his wife is alive—that she does not want to remain among us. She wants to go back, and in a few days she will be back." The next week he took me out part of the way in a cart—to go further, he was afraid. And I went alone towards <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>—I can't remember how many kilometers. I arrived in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. It's the same story again—how does one get in—into the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName>? And then it occurred to me that my father had a chauffeur, a Christian, a decent man.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1444.894" end="x">He had a what?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1445.925" end="x">A chauffeur.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1446.768" end="x">A chauffeur?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1447.627" end="x">A driver.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1448.643" end="x">(hesitantly) Did he have a --?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1449.830" end="x">(interrupting) Yes, my father-in-law, had--</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1451.033" end="x">An automobile?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1452.596" end="x">Yes. He was a good business man; so he had an automobile and a driver—a very decent person. He lives now in the yard of the house that once belonged to my father-in-law. So I went to him. He didn't know me, but I gave the name of Meyer Kovitzki, and he said: "Don't be afraid. You can be with me as long as you want." But he had a wife and a child, and I did not want to cause him anxiety. So I went down to the cellar, and he went to the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName> to find out about things, and Friday morning his own wife went with me through the streets, and she led me to the <placeName ref="Grodno Ghetto" type="camp">ghetto</placeName>. Then another Pole helped me to get in. But before I went in, he told me: "You know where you are going?" And I said, "Where is my man, and where is my place?" That was on Friday noon. I was there all night until five o'clock in the morning. At five o'clock in the morning again shooting and screaming. A new transport. And I and my husband went to this transport towards the synagogue. Then the whole night we stayed in the synagogue. In the synagogue it was crowded—heavy and crowded. One could not breathe. The whole night without a drop of water, and outside the shooting. At two o'clock in the morning we were driven out to the train. And my husband said: "No, you are not going to die. Because you have returned to me, is that why you should perish?" And I said, "I cannot be—I am already tired. Maybe I shall rest in the grave." But he did not wish to understand, and just one street away from the train he pushed me into a gate, in spite of the guards, because it was still dark. We remained standing in the gateway until morning. We both took off our [yellow] patches. What to do now?</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1556.642" end="x">He with you?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1557.829" end="x">Yes. What to do now? Where to go? A city where everybody knew my husband. Again I went to the suburb, again to an acquaintance, a Christian woman. We washed and got ready to start out at night. We rested up, then wandered on. No arms, no money, nothing. If we only could reach the <term ref="#vothG_partisans">partisans</term>—at least to sell our lives dearly! . . . But where are the <term ref="#vothG_partisans">partisans</term>? They tell us 150 kilometers away, and one had to go in the direction of Stutin.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1593.427" end="x">Stutin?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1595.037" end="x">Stutin. [She apparently refers to <placeName ref="Szczecin">Szczecin</placeName>] One night I had it easy—a woman—I looked like a Christian. I do not know where to spend the night. In Nieman we went into a little house. There lived a widow, A Christian—I don't know her name—with her son. It was dangerous for them—it was hazardous. But they took us in and gave us a place to sleep and watched all night, in case the Germans might come. She had a son whom they wanted to drag away to work, and in the morning they gave my man shaving things, and they gave me plenty of food, and at night we slept in an open shack, and in the morning we marched on. Not all <term ref="#vothG_whiteR">WhiteRussians</term> were that way. Another after giving us food reported us: "Two people have passed by—must be Jews." And we were taken to the <term ref="#vothG_gestapo">Gestapo</term>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1595.037" end="x">You?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1595.037" end="x">I and my man. [A pause, she weeps convulsively.]</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1595.037" end="x">In the <term ref="#vothG_gestapo">gestapo</term>—I don't known what happened there. When I saw my man receiving the first blow, something tore apart in me. I don't know what happened. My man was being beaten: "My wife is Polish—you are making a mistake. She wants to die with me together. But this is not true; she is not a Jewess." And then he asked me: "Are you a Jewess?" "Yes, I am Jewish."—"That is nonsense, you do not look Jewish."—"Still I am Jewish." But my man continued repeating that I was a Christian until they were taken by doubts. There was a Polish policeman present. <term ref="#vothG_whiteR">WhiteRussians</term> in dark blue uniforms. "Oh, so you are loving a Jew?" And I replied: "I am Jewish. I am not ashamed." The whole night they kept us locked up, calling us out separately. My husband and then me alone, then both of us together. My husband whispered to me, "I plead with you, go try to live. Go back to <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. You will be a mother to the child. Maybe you will tell her some day that she had a father." And I yielded, and I went out to live.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1656.844" end="x">What do you mean, to live?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1657.703" end="x">Then before they led me away, the <term ref="#vothG_gestapo">Gestapo</term> man said, "I give you my word, you will live and your husband will live." Here I was being separated from my man—could one believe them? And still it was a ray of hope. [A prolonged spell of weeping sets in.]</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1792.073" end="x">(Into the microphone) We are lighting our cigarettes. I can't find any water. [To Anna] Nu?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1795.995" end="x">I was transported away to a <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term>. There were <term ref="#vothG_whiteR">WhiteRussians</term>, criminals, Poles. People who have slaughtered a----.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1808.262" end="x">You were not set free?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1809.637" end="x">No, I was sent to the <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term>, together with <term ref="#vothG_aryan">Aryans</term>. <term ref="#vothG_whiteR">WhiteRussians</term>. Women who have been peddling liquor. Those who had slaughtered a calf without a permit. And there they held me for observation. The first three weeks I constantly argued that I was a Jewess. "Don't hold me here. My place is with the other Jews." But if one is still alive after three weeks, one adjusts to the idea that one has to stay alive, and now I said nothing And then in time I would myself claim to be a Christian . . . [Here is a short break in the wire, about two words missing.] In a few weeks, I can't remember any more exactly, they shipped me to Germany, together with a transport of Gentiles, to work in East Prussia. I really don't remember what happened to me. Up to the time I was shipped to <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>, I was like half-conscious. It was the worst—(and then apparently answering a question of Boder's that did not come through the microphone) Tattooed? 257539—correction 82529 and a triangle.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1898.898" end="x">The triangle means Jewish?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1901.789" end="x">Yes.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1908.023" end="x">Go ahead.</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1909.085" end="x">All the time I tried to take hold of myself. I had decided that I must live. Now I can tell what was hardest to bear. It was the satisfaction of those Poles and <term ref="#vothG_whiteR">WhiteRussians</term>—not like those that gave me shelter. There were all kinds of them. And they spoke of the extermination of the Jews—with all the details.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1930.670" end="x">Were you taken to <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> as a Jew?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1933.170" end="x">Later I reported to the "police" that I was a Jewess. I wanted to die together with the Jews than to live this way. They did not believe me. They thought I must have gone crazy because my husband was taken away. After that they held me for a month in a <placeName ref="Koenigsberg">Koenigsberg</placeName> prison, and then I was sent to <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. By the time of our arrival at <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>, I had lost all semblance of a human being. Now when I encountered people who have seen me in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>, they tell me . . . [here she begins to sob violently, and the whole sentence sounds incoherent. It is possible that by slowing down the wire we could get the words. We will do that later, but now we are continuing with the next sentence. The last few words seem to sound like: "I saw him everywhere among people."] I believed it was real. In <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> I met a girl friend from <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>, and she told me that the oldest daughter of my brother has remained alive, as well as the wife of my youngest brother. Both are in a working camp in . . . [the name of the city is not clear.] Then I was taken by hope that I would see them. And that gave me some courage, in spite of the fact that in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> I was a complete so-called <term ref="#vothG_mussulman">Mussulman</term>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="1998.221" end="x">You?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="1998.846" end="x">Yes, I was a <term ref="#vothG_mussulman">Mussulman</term>. A kind of people who wouldn't eat. I could not eat. There was food, but I could not eat. I was sick. I was sick at my mouth. I don't know what they called that sickness. A kind of eruption. Then my tongue became completely hard. My legs were covered with boils. Then my illness from before—gall stones—In <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>—in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> not to appear to the <term ref="#vothG_appell">appell</term> meant death, and still the supervisers of the barracks had pity on me and let me remain on the cot up to the last moment when already the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men had come for roll call. Then they would drag me off the cot and lead me out. In <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> I had a change of mind. I decided again to live. There appeared one day in my <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term> a distant cousin of mine, a girl, Nelly Kovitzka, a seventeen-year old girl. Her face was that of my little girl. And I was overcome with hope I should return. Maybe she is alive . . . [three or four words unintelligible]. And I started to fight again, to struggle for life, in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. I became a- I was cleaning the <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term>. A <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term> that housed thirteen hundred people. I cleaned it, I scrubbed it, and for that I would get another helping of soup, and at times I would get a little piece of bread that the blokova would leave uneaten. Then in spite of curfew I dressed up. In <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> there was enough to wear. There was the clothing of the dead. They were burning people every day. The whole night the ovens would flame, and the skies red, dark red, just like . . . . [the next word is not clear.] One night I was standing in front of the <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term>. A Christian <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term> <term ref="#vothG_trusty">trusty</term> stood near by. That night they were burning from the Gypsy <term ref="#vothG_lager">Lager</term>. I don't know how many thousands were there.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2124.297" end="x">Who were in the Gypsy <term ref="#vothG_lager">Lager</term>?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2126.453" end="x">The Gypsy camp was a camp where there were Gypsies exclusively. They were not tattooed. They were assembled there, and then they all were burned. I don't know. Possibly they were not even gassed, because of the horrible screams coming from there. Moreover one could somehow feel it. And there I was standing, and I mumbled to myself, and I said, "Dante was just a dog. They know it much better." And the Christian woman heard it, and she said to me [and here she imitates a voice of extreme surprise], "You know about Dante? How do you come to know anything about Dante?" She thought that I always must have been looking like that—like in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. And from that night we became friends.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2163.364" end="x">A Christian woman?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2164.036" end="x">A Christian woman. She was a <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term>
                        <term ref="#vothG_trusty">trusty</term>. And she had the say over life and death. But she was a human being. Only afterwards I realized that she was a human being. In spite of the fact that she would beat us, and in spite of all that, she was fighting for the life of every prisoner. For the Christians she did not have to fight. Christians normally did not go to the ovens, only those who had died. But for the Jews she had to fight. Two years ago [this with some hidden light in her voice] on Rosh Hashona [the interview was taking place on Rosh Hashona of 1946, and she apparently refers to an incident exactly two years before] just two years ago, there was to be a selection. A selection was when they re-sorted the people—who for the ovens and who should stay alive. So she took all the weak and the sick, including myself, and sent them away outside the <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term> for work, Aussenkomando, so they should not be present for the "selection." However, there was no selection afterwards. But I became convinced that she was really human, that if she mistreated and beat us, it was only because she herself wanted to survive and wanted us to survive.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2224.750" end="x">She was a Christian?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2225.828" end="x">(emphatically) A Christian woman. But she wanted to earn the confidence of the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men. She was a political prisoner.. A very intelligent woman, from <placeName ref="Warsaw">Warsaw</placeName>, a colonel's daughter. I stayed on in the <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term> for part of a year. I was gravely ill with gallstones. So she herself cooked me some food that I could stand, and she shielded me and reported that I am working for her and that I do not have to go to work. By the end of the summer there passed through <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> my brother's daughter and my brothers wife. They again told me that I am the oldest in our family and that I must live.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2265.532" end="x">What does it mean, they passed through?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2267.486" end="x">They were transported through <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> to a work <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term> in the direction of <placeName ref="Zabrze">Hindenburg</placeName>. They were in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> only a few hours.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2274.852" end="x">Then you have seen them?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2276.258" end="x">Yes, somebody came and told me; I went over there and managed to see them. But afterwards I did not believe that they were taken to a work camp, because nobody believes that one can come out alive from <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>, although the Red Army was already at the gates of <placeName ref="Warsaw">Warsaw</placeName>. In September more transports were sent away, and we didn't know where to. In October I decided to get away from <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. Be what it may, better come death, but no <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. To have to look on how living human beings stand in line waiting for death, and to say nothing, and they don't even cry. They would not cry. Once the Christian <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term>
                        <term ref="#vothG_trusty">trustys</term> reproached me: "Why are they going with such indifference to death? Why don't they fight? Why don't they kill somebody?" So I replied, "You haven't been in a <term ref="#vothG_ghetto">ghetto</term>. You have not seen how Jews went away in transports with congealed nerves [verglievert]. A human being can cry himself dry; a human being clings to life, and up to the last moment there is a ray of hope and they are defenseless. And they have no arms. How can you say that? Maybe you just want to soothe your conscience talking that way." And the same day a miracle happened. The Jews seized the oven. They first threw in some forty <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men, and then, with them one hundred-fifty lost their lives, and a hundred-fifty ran away into the woods to the <term ref="#vothG_partisans">partisans</term>. Of course, it was with help from outside, of <term ref="#vothG_partisans">partisans</term>.- of Poles and other nationalities.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2371.530" end="x">Do you really know that for sure?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2373.717" end="x">[with excitement] I was present and now in . . . there was a girl, Kathe. She now has left for the land of Israel, in . . . [Here she gives a name of a place which I cannot understand. It sounds like Alia Beth]. And it was she personally who threw in the bomb. I was then assigned to outside work, and I have seen it myself, and so shall I see the delivery of all the Jews.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2388.858" end="x">Do you mean to say that they threw the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men into the oven?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2392.077" end="x">That was a few kilometers from our <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term>, Breginski. The commandos that were doing the burning were Jews. There were about fifty people present . . .</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2405.985" end="x">And you?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2406.767" end="x">They were guarded by <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men, and then they were . . . (pause, and the conversation becomes incoherent), and then I just heard the explosion, and when I came out I saw the oven in flames. And then we heard shooting. The result was that the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men were caught unawares, and they threw them into the burning oven, and afterwards -</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2447.150" end="x">How can forty people be thrown into one oven?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2449.916" end="x">Those were such pits—[the recording becomes rather confused; and is not at all clear]. They threw them in, and afterwards they blasted the oven. One hundred-fifty were shot, and one hundred-fifty got away into the woods. And I thought then, maybe we shall still survive. An answer has come to what she had said the about the Jews. If others would be saying it, I wouldn't care; but if such a Christian, who was so valuable to us and respected, [should think that way]—that we cared. Why should she say the Jews have no courage? That hurts. And now this happens. In October they began to assemble transports from <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. I had no hope to get away with the transport, because I looked very sick, but I dressed, and I painted myself for each <term ref="#vothG_appell">appell</term>, to give myself color—they shouldn't see my deadly paleness.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2510.197" end="x">What were you doing?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2511.103" end="x">For each <term ref="#vothG_appell">appell</term> I painted my face, so they shouldn't see how terribly pale I was.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2515.637" end="x">Where did you get the stuff?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2516.887" end="x">Well, there would come transports of Jews from all over the world, and they did not know what their fate would be. So every woman still had these things. And they would lie on the dumps, and those who had access to the dumps would collect it and would give it to everyone who looked bad, to cover it up. And so I was heavily painted. One day they came to our <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term> and told us that we are going to the transport—to lead us to a transport <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term>. And I too was selected during the <term ref="#vothG_appell">appell</term>. And so we went to <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term> 31, the transit <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term>. Here we remained for eight days. Then there was a selection and we were sent to the shower bath. That was a bathing room, where people would bathe, and afterward everyone was looked over. For me that was very dangerous; so a woman, a <term ref="#vothG_block">block</term> servant, told me: "Don't go in there. Simply sneak out through the other side and stand up with those on the right side, because externally you look well." And so I mingled in with three hundred other women, and I went away with a transport to <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName>. In <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName> there was work. In <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName> there was no work. In <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName> they manufactured ammunition, and there the strength to live returned to me. To work!—I should stamp cartridges for machine guns, with which the Germans would shoot (and these were the last munition factories) the Americans who came to liberate us! And because I looked so [decrepit] they thought that I was such a fool! In a few days I learned the mechanism of my machine, and in a few days I started to work very ardently. The assigned quota was twelve thousand, but I would produce fifteen thousand pieces. But fifteen thousand smaller ones and fifteen thousand larger ones, never the caliber that was prescribed. When they discovered it, there were eighty thousand rejected pieces. My foreman came over to me and said: "If you do it once more, I shall chop off your hand." So I said, "Oh [here her voice becomes ironical, and she speaks in perfect German], you can report that I am doing sabotage? Then they make me altogether kaput." "Oh, for that you are much too dumb!" I don't know, maybe he had noticed what I was doing, but it may have been too late, and he already was responsible along with me. I can't be so naive as to assume that the Germans wanted to cooperate with me against Hitler. Such do not exist. But to the last moment they had fate. In the faces of the Germans I read just like in a newspaper. They were very sad the last days. It was already the year 1945, in March. They still drove us to work, and they would beat us at every air raid alarm. But, thank God! The air raid alarm would last for twenty-four hours. They would run into the air raid shelter, and we would run right out into the yard. We would run out into the yard, and laugh, and the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men would say to us: "Aren't you afraid? Do you think that your friends will spare you?" [She continues with laughter in her voice] "You are afraid! Why aren't you in the battlefield? All you are fighting with is eight hundred defenseless and weak women. That is the kind of heroes you are!" The girls thought that I was again insane, like I had been in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. But it was indifferent to me. [Here again the record loses its clearness]. To die in such a fashion may be well worth while. The 27th of March we were driven out of <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2710.152" end="x">1945 or 1944?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2713.183" end="x">1945. They drove us out from <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName>—at night we were evacuated. We were to go to <placeName ref="Bergen-Belsen concentration camp" type="camp">Bergen-Belsen</placeName> [ this with irony in her voice]. They couldn't take us any more to <placeName ref="Bergen-Belsen concentration camp" type="camp">Bergen-Belsen</placeName>, but they didn't know. Driven at night and during the day locked up in shops. [In the midst of her German she uses the English word "shops". That is one of those new words that was adopted into the German language during the war]. They had everything ready to finish us off. But there was no more time.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2733.729" end="x">What do you mean, finish you off?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2735.463" end="x">They had orders not to release us alive. On the third day at dawn we remained standing in a little lane, deep in mud, and the top division leader was frothing at his mouth. We heard already the rumbling American tanks, and we were led into the woods. I don't know how they happened not to hit us. So he says (he still yelled then), "You band of Jew-pigs." And he left us alone with all the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men, and he himself ran away. So I said then to one of the girls, "You know, I don't know whether we shall survive, but he will not come back any more." So she says: "I have a half a bread and I give you this half a bread if that should happen the way you say." And I still thought that I would have a chance to eat that half a bread in case he should not return. But it has become very late. And it happened the first of April, 1945, a quarter of nine. Shooting!</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2798.717" end="x">In the evening or in the morning?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2799.880" end="x">In the morning. Shooting, [with joy in her voice] Americans! They are shooting at us, and here we are, together with the <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men, lying under the trees. The bullets whistled. [She uses the expression—bullets burned]. And we laughed—crazy of us. The <term ref="#vothG_ss">SS</term> men stood around. They were no heroes any more. They don't know where to run. Only five minutes before, they wouldn't run away. They could not leave us alone. They still believed in the <term ref="#vothG_fuehrer">Fuehrer</term>. And now they were standing with their arms down. They were still ordering to go to the "shops", but nobody went. We remained lying down right there. The Americans fired three times, and then a silence came over us. An aeroplane came down at low altitude, and a white flag [here she sobs again], and it was spread out.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2848.668" end="x">What do you mean, a white flag?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2850.075" end="x">The Germans raised a white flag. The name of the town is <placeName ref="Kaunitz">Kaunitz</placeName>, in Westphalia near <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName>, twenty-seven kilometers from <placeName ref="Lippstadt II concentration camp" type="camp">Lippstadt</placeName>. And here we were, almost crazy. We haven't a strip of a white thing. Somebody had a bandage around a wounded leg, and that bandage was raised at an approaching American tank, and the women prostrated themselves on the ground, kissing the wheels. The Americans thought it was a house of the insane. They looked at us. [I am not sure of the correct translation of the next few sentences.] And how we looked! All in tatters. [Her words are barely audible.] And speaking—nobody could. We were all speechless. And then he understood, and two tears rolled down his face. [Again the text is not clear, she is very upset.] And until the others arrived, he wept with us. Not a Jew—a Christian. And then they began to arrive, the tanks. It was Passover. The last day of it. And matzos [Unleavened bread, eaten by Jews at Easter] fell from the tanks. And chocolate and cigarettes. And they would jump off the tanks and they were kissing us. Us dirty and lousy ones. "Do not weep," they would say. But we wept more and again. And incessantly the tears ran. The Ninth Army had not seen any Jews in Germany, and we thought that we were the only Jewish survivors, and we did not want to live. But they consoled us. They were telling us that there were many other armies that have reached other <term ref="#vothG_lager">lagers</term> which were liberated. That was liberation. We were all dead sick. I was half swollen. Immediately the American army led us into homes. They burned everything we had on us, although we wanted to save the clothing. But it was all infected, and we were afraid to keep it. Dirty. And we changed our clothes, putting on whatever we could. We could take things, good things, from the Germans. We took it from the Germans [with irony in her voice], they gave it to us themselves. They were afraid now. We dressed [here her voice again breaks into sobs]. We washed ourselves, with soap, warm water, a clean towel, pure underwear. [She uses the English word "pure"]. Oh! The Americans themselves were crazy with joy. They now understood—"You are going to liberate human beings." And that army hadn't seen before those who were liberated. We were the first ones, and they were rejoicing like little children. And in the evening one American put on his head a hat, a German hat, a womans hat, and another one played some kind of instrument, and he danced with a little girl from our <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term>. I shall not forget it, ever. [She weeps again and speaks in exhaustion.] For the first time we got into the <term ref="#vothG_lager">lager</term> a radio, and we heard the news. <placeName ref="Bergen-Belsen concentration camp" type="camp">Bergen-Belsen</placeName> liberated. Thirty thousand hopelessly sick. Thousands and thousands dead. Who knows whether my people were there? Everybody thought so, and their eyes would run out [in tears.] <placeName ref="Buchenwald concentration camp" type="camp">Buchenwald</placeName>.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="2887.219" end="x"><term ref="#vothG_lager">Lagers</term>?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="2888.375" end="x">Liberated. Should it be possible that anyone would be found. That anyone should have survived? And I am here already a year. I searched. I found a daughter of my brother.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3045.013" end="x">Where?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3045.607" end="x">She was in <placeName ref="Bergen-Belsen concentration camp" type="camp">Bergen-Belsen</placeName>. The Rabbi Shubow brought her, the daughter and my brother's wife.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3054.278" end="x">An American Rabbi?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3055.841" end="x">Joseph Shubow from <placeName ref="Boston">Boston</placeName>. Joseph Shubow from <placeName ref="Boston">Boston</placeName>. He was with us.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3060.011" end="x">Where are they now?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3061.323" end="x">My sister-in-law is now in Norway. She has an aunt there. And my brother's daughter [she starts weeping again] returned to Poland to bring her brothers who also remained alive. And with this in <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>,—I learned the whole story—the whole <term ref="#vothG_pogrom">pogrom</term>, and my eyes ran out [in tears] from horror. The community of my father, it consisted of twenty-four thousand Jews, and only three hundred remained. And lately there were only a hundred Jews, and forty-two were killed in <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>. And my brother's son was recently in <placeName ref="Kielce">Kielce</placeName>—about twenty years of age. Now he is in <placeName ref="Lódź">Lodz</placeName> and has a little baby. His wife recently gave birth to the child, and that is why he can't come yet. I hope every moment that they will arrive. My father had twenty-four grandchildren. My little daughter was the twenty-fifth. I don't have my child. Three weeks before the arrival of the Red Army, the woman was reported, and they took away my child and the woman.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3123.546" end="x">The Germans?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3124.983" end="x">The Germans. They were in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName> in 1944. That I know now. And the child was murderously shot. After liberation the woman [she chokes in tears with the next word—one understands it by inference] exhumed the child, and the physician who had delivered the baby was present when she was exhumed from a grave in a Christian cemetery. The Jewish cemetery does not exist any more in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. It was desecrated.</u>
                    <!-- end spool 9-165 -->
                    <!-- begin spool 9-166 -->
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3158.541" end="x">[In English] <placeName ref="Wiesbaden">Wiesbaden</placeName>, September the 26th, 1946. I am struggling with time. Mrs. Kaletska is going over to the third spool and I want to let her finish.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3171.575" end="x">[In Yiddish] Let's have it again. What were you telling me about your baby?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3174.528" end="x">Last year, about the end of the year, I went to Poland with the hope to find my child. I arrived in <placeName ref="Lódź">Lodz</placeName>, and the wife of the doctor told me the child was not alive, that the Christian woman was thrown in jail because she was reported.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3193.172" end="x">But the Christian woman was in <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3195.063" end="x">Yes, she [apparently the doctor's wife] also came from <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. She was evacuated from <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName> and came to <placeName ref="Lódź">Lodz</placeName>. That Christian woman was held in jail with the child. An investigation was made, and it was found out that she had picked up the child on the street. They established then that it was a Jewish child, and they . . . [here she cuts off a word which she started to say and which apparently means "killed it." It is also possible that she did not finish the sentence because the meaning was obvious and because she was interrupted by the interviewer].</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3215.026" end="x">How could they establish that the girl was a Jewish child?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3217.651" end="x">They—I don't know how they established it. Possibly somebody reported to them, because the child looked later very much like my husband. The Kovitzki's were a well-known family, and they all resembled each other very much. It was also suspicious, because the woman was childless, and she had not given away the child to an orphanage.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3241.964" end="x">Oh, she did not place the child in an orphanage?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3243.370" end="x">Because she loved the child, she kept the child like her own. And she left for me a present—a few pictures. I will show them to you right away. [As I remember it, she looked in her pocketbook.] Oh, no. I don't have them with me. And they buried the child three weeks before the Red Army marched in. When the Red Army arrived the woman interfered, requesting a permit to bury the child. It was said that I apparently was not alive any more; but they wanted to remove the child from the Christian cemetery. The Jewish cemetery was entirely desecrated.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3277.224" end="x">Have you seen the woman afterwards?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3279.146" end="x">No, the woman I haven't seen any more.</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3280.334" end="x">So, how did you get the pictures?</u>
                    <u who="#kaletskaA" start="3281.849" end="x">The pictures she left with a woman friend of mine who was saved. She lived on "<term ref="#vothG_aryan">Aryan</term> papers" near <placeName ref="Hrodna">Grodno</placeName>. About twelve kilometers from there. And this woman friend of mine went to this [Christian] woman and wanted to take my child back. So she gave her the pictures. And so I don't have the child. Then there was a rumor that my husband was alive, Jacob Kovitzki. Somebody wrote from <placeName ref="Kaunas">Kovno</placeName>, but I didn't know where he is, and a year has passed. I was unable to find him. Maybe he went into Russia, but so far there is nothing from him. Now I am working in <placeName ref="Pfalzheim">Pfalzheim</placeName>, in a kindergarten. There are twenty little Jewish children. And I play with them, and then I forget about all that. Again I have around me Jewish children. But after work, to come alone to my room—today is a holiday. Where are all mine, who used to celebrate the holidays with me? Thank God! There are Jews staying with me on a holiday. Not a holiday in <placeName ref="Auschwitz concentration camp" type="camp">Auschwitz</placeName>. But my people are no more. I am alone. [This whole section on Spool 167 was spoken with sobs, which are clearly heard on the wire. The woman was very much beside herself. I had a hard time to keep her in line with the microphone, and now I don't find a little episode which she told me, apparently after I had stopped the machine. It is not on the wire, but here it is, written from memory: "Last night, and that means on the first evening of Rosh Hashona we, like at home, prepared the holiday meal, and as was customary at home, we invited a soldier to share it with us. But this time it was not a poor soldier, away from home, who had to be fed, but an American Jewish soldier, who, accepting the invitation, brought us an armful of gifts, all kinds of American food and delicacies."]</u>
                    <u who="#boderD" start="3368.180" end="x">[In English] We have to conclude, my automobile is waiting. [unintelligible] . . . very valuable material, that I have to cancel another appointment. <placeName ref="Wiesbaden">Wiesbaden</placeName>, September the 46th, in the synagogue that was desecrated in 1937 or '38, and which had its holiday service for the first time today, although not yet re-dedicated. What we have heard from this woman . . . is about a story what we have heard from everybody. I'm concluding my project in Germany, and I want to thank the <term ref="#vothG_unrra">UNRRA</term>, Jack Thompson from the Chicago Tribune, Paul and Ms. Gurman, Morris Alther, Henry McCarthy and Harriet McCarthy, my daughter Elena Boder and my son in law, Ledewitz, Dave Siegel, and all those who made this project possible. Ben Weintraub, and Eve in <placeName ref="München">Munich</placeName>. And also Salk. I can't speak, I don't recall, remember the names now because I am just in a trance after this woman's report. I am concluding this project, the automobile is waiting, I am going to <placeName ref="Frankfurt am Main">Frankfurt</placeName>. Who is going to sit in judgment of all this, and who is going to judge my work? Illinois Institute of Technology wire recording. I am leaving tonight for <placeName ref="Paris">Paris</placeName>, the project is concluded.</u>
                </div>
                <!-- end spool 9-166 -->
            </div>
            <!-- end English translation -->
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
